<?xml-model href="../../Sch%C3%A9mas/ampere.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Correspondance d'André-Marie Ampère - Lettre 942</title>
                <author>Faraday, Michael</author>
                <editor>Christine Blondel</editor>
                <editor>Marco Segala</editor>
                <funder>ANR Corpus 2012</funder>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Christine Blondel, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre
                        Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
                    <resp>Responsable du projet, édition</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Marco Segala, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
                    <resp>Responsable du projet, édition</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Delphine Usal, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
                    <resp>Gestion de bases de données</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Aude Coustumer, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
                    <resp>Relecture et encodage en XML/TEI P5</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Philippe Pons, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
                    <resp>Responsable informatique, relecture et encodage en XML/TEI P5</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Marie-Hélène Wronecki, <affiliation>CRHST</affiliation>
          </name>
                    <resp>Édition web</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Florence Greffe, <affiliation>Archives de l'Académie des
                            sciences</affiliation>
          </name>
                    <resp>Mise en place de la numérisation</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <respStmt>
          <name>Mathilde Dutertre, </name>
          <resp>Stagiaire ENC (École nationale des chartes) au Centre Alexandre Koyré : élaboration du schéma XML TEI et encodage</resp>
        </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent/>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS)</authority>
                <publisher>Centre Alexandre Koyré - CNRS (UMR 8560)</publisher>
                <address>
          <addrLine>27 rue Damesme</addrLine>
          <addrLine>75013 Paris</addrLine>
        </address>
                <distributor>
          <name>Centre de calcul de
                    l'IN2P3</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>Domaine scientifique de la Doua</addrLine>
            <addrLine>43 boulevard du 11 Novembre 1918</addrLine>
            <addrLine>69622 Villeurbanne Cedex</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
                <availability>
          <p>Ce texte est protégé par la licence <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode">Creative Commons</ref> dont le contenu est disponible sous Creative Commons Attribution -Non commercial - No Derivative Works 4.0 France</p>
        </availability>
                <date/>
                <idno/>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct xml:id="ampere_corr_L1825-11-17-a">
                    <monogr xmlns="">
                        <editor>
                            <surname>James</surname>
                            <forename>Frank A. J. L.</forename>
                        </editor>
                        <title>The Correspondence of Michael Faraday</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>IEE</publisher>
                            <biblScope type="vol">vol. 1 (1811-1831)</biblScope>
                            <date when="1991">1991</date>
                            <biblScope type="pp">Letter 275, pp. 392-393 </biblScope>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>


                    
                <idno type="old">L942</idno>
        </biblStruct>
                <listWit>
                    <witness xml:id="L942manuscrit">
            <msDesc type="original_manuscrit">
                            <msIdentifier>
                                <country xmlns="">États-Unies</country>
                                <settlement xmlns="">Washington</settlement>
                                <institution xmlns="">Smithsonian Institution Library</institution>
                                <repository xmlns="">Dibner Collection</repository>
                                <idno xmlns="">MS 554A [note de Franck JAMES]</idno>
                            </msIdentifier>
                        </msDesc>
          </witness>
                </listWit>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p>Les erreurs flagrantes de fond ou de forme ont été corrigées.</p>
                </correction>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p>Les retours à la ligne des documents originaux sont respectés.</p>
                </hyphenation>
                <normalization>
                    <p>L'orthographe et la ponctuation ont été normalisées.</p>
                    <p>Les noms propres avec des graphies différentes ont été normalisés.</p>
                </normalization>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName type="sender">Faraday, Michael</persName>
          <date when-iso="1825-11-17">17 novembre 1825</date>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName type="adressee">Ampère, André-Marie</persName>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
            <creation>
        <date when="2014-07">juillet 2014</date>
        <name>Philippe Pons</name>
        <name>Aude
                    Coustumer</name>
      </creation>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="fra">Français</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text type="correspondance" decls="#ampere_corr_L1825-11-17-a">
        <body>
            <div>
                <opener>
          <date when="1825-11-17">17 November 1825</date>
        </opener>
                <p>
          <foreign xml:lang="eng">My dear Sir I have had great pleasure at different times lately by the receipt of
                    your kind letters sent by our mutual friends M. <persName>de la Rive</persName>, Mr. <persName>South</persName> and Mr.
                    <persName>Underwood</persName> though it has so happened that by my absence from town &amp;c. none
                    but that by Mr. <persName>South</persName> reached me in due time. I beg at this opportunity to
                    return you my sincere thanks for your kindness in sending me copies of your
                    papers, these I value highly not only for their intrinsic merit but also because
                    they are so many marks of your kind estimation of myself. And I hope you will
                    never fail to mark them as from yourself by writing on the title page. I only
                    wish that I were competent more frequently to make proper acknowledgements for
                    them by similar returns. Every letter you write me states how busily you are
                    engaged and I cannot wish it otherwise knowing how well your time is spent. Much
                    of mine is unfortunately occupied in very common place employment and this I may
                    offer as an excuse (for want of a better) for the little I do in original
                    research. I am sorry to find by one of your letters that you experience an
                    unworthy opposition to the fair &amp; high claim you have to the approbation and
                    thanks of your fellow Philosophers. This however you can hardly wonder at. I do
                    not know what it is or by whom exerted in your case but I never yet even in my
                    short time knew a man to do anything eminent or become worthy of distinction
                    without becoming at the same time obnoxious to the cavils and rude encounters of
                    envious men. Little as I have done, I have experienced it and that too where I
                    least expected it. I think however and hope that you are somewhat mistaken in
                    your opinion of the feeling here. It is true that some of your views were at
                    first received here with great reserve but I think now that all your facts are
                    admitted and are all properly attributed to you. With regard to your theory it
                    so soon becomes mathematical that it quickly gets beyond my reach at the same
                    time I know that it has received the consideration of eminent men here - I am
                    not however competent to tell you exactly how it is accepted, for in fact being
                    a very busy man and somewhat retired in habits I am all day long in my
                    Laboratory, do not go much among scientific men and am in some sort an anchorite
                    in the Scientific world. Hence I have neither time nor opportunity for
                    scientific conversation and am frequently surprised at information which is new
                    to me when old to every one else. Be assured however that whenever the
                    opportunity occurs I do full justice to your important investigations for as far
                    I can go with them, I am convinced their accuracy &amp; great value. Many thanks
                    to you for M. <persName>Demonferrand</persName>'s book. I had it only a day or two ago - and though I
                    have not yet read it, have looked over the table &amp; agree with you in its
                    accuracy. I am My dear Sir Your Very Obliged &amp; faithful friend M.
                    <persName>Faraday</persName>
          </foreign>
        </p>
                <closer> M. <persName>Ampère</persName>, &amp;c &amp;c </closer>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>