<?xml-model href="../../Sch%C3%A9mas/ampere.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Correspondance d'André-Marie Ampère - Lettre 940</title>
            <author>Faraday, Michael</author>
            <editor>Christine Blondel</editor>
            <editor>Marco Segala</editor>
            <funder>ANR Corpus 2012</funder>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Christine Blondel, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
               <resp>Responsable du projet, édition</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Marco Segala, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          <affiliation>Università L'Aquila</affiliation>
          </name>
               <resp>Responsable du projet, édition</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Delphine Usal, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
               <resp>Gestion de bases de données</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Aude Coustumer, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
               <resp>Relecture et encodage en XML/TEI P5</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Philippe Pons, <affiliation>Centre Alexandre Koyré</affiliation>
          </name>
               <resp>Responsable informatique, relecture et encodage en XML/TEI P5</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Marie-Hélène Wronecki, <affiliation>CRHST</affiliation>
          </name>
               <resp>Édition web</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Florence Greffe, <affiliation>Archives de l'Académie des
                  sciences</affiliation>
          </name>
               <resp>Mise en place de la numérisation</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <respStmt>
          <name>Mathilde Dutertre, </name>
          <resp>Stagiaire ENC (École nationale des chartes) au Centre Alexandre Koyré : élaboration du schéma XML TEI et encodage</resp>
        </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent/>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique (CNRS)</authority>
            <publisher>Centre Alexandre Koyré - CNRS (UMR 8560)</publisher>
            <address>
          <addrLine>27 rue Damesme</addrLine>
          <addrLine>75013 Paris</addrLine>
        </address>
            <distributor>
          <name>Centre de calcul de
               l'IN2P3</name>
          <address>
            <addrLine>Domaine scientifique de la Doua</addrLine>
            <addrLine>43 boulevard du 11 Novembre 1918</addrLine>
            <addrLine>69622 Villeurbanne Cedex</addrLine>
          </address>
        </distributor>
            <availability>
          <p>Ce texte est protégé par la licence <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/legalcode">Creative Commons</ref> dont le contenu est disponible sous Creative Commons Attribution -Non commercial - No Derivative Works 4.0 France</p>
        </availability>
            <date/>
            <idno/>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct xml:id="ampere_corr_L1823-07-01-a">
               <monogr xmlns="">
                  <editor>
                     <surname>James</surname>
                     <forename>Frank A. J. L.</forename>
                  </editor>
                  <title>The Correspondence of Michael Faraday</title>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>IEE</publisher>
                     <biblScope type="vol">vol. 1 (1811-1831)</biblScope>
                     <date when="1991">1991</date>
                     <biblScope type="pp">Letter 203, p. 320-321</biblScope>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
               
            <idno type="old">L940</idno>
        </biblStruct>
            <listWit>
               <witness xml:id="L940manuscrit">
            <msDesc type="original_manuscrit">
                     <msIdentifier>
                        <country xmlns="">États-Unies</country>
                        <settlement xmlns="">New York</settlement>
                        <institution xmlns="">Columbia University Library</institution>
                        <repository xmlns="">Gen. MS Coll. Faraday [note de Franck
                           JAMES]</repository>
                     </msIdentifier>
                  </msDesc>
          </witness>
            </listWit>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p/>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction>
               <p>Les erreurs flagrantes de fond ou de forme ont été corrigées.</p>
            </correction>
            <hyphenation>
               <p>Les retours à la ligne des documents originaux sont respectés.</p>
            </hyphenation>
            <normalization>
               <p>L'orthographe et la ponctuation ont été normalisées.</p>
               <p>Les noms propres avec des graphies différentes ont été normalisés.</p>
            </normalization>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
      <correspDesc>
        <correspAction type="sent">
          <persName type="sender">Faraday, Michael</persName>
          <date when-iso="1823-07-01">1er juillet
                  1823</date>
        </correspAction>
        <correspAction type="received">
          <persName type="adressee">Ampère, André-Marie</persName>
        </correspAction>
      </correspDesc>
         <creation>
        <date when="2014-07">juillet 2014</date>
        <name>Philippe Pons</name>
        <name>Aude
               Coustumer</name>
      </creation>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="fra">Français</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change/>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text type="correspondance" decls="#ampere_corr_L1823-07-01-a">
      <body>
         <div>
            <opener>
          <date when="1823-07-01">1 July 1823</date>
        </opener>
            <p>
          <foreign xml:lang="eng">Dear Sir Every letter of mine to you either is, or ought to be, a letter of thanks
               for I constantly find myself indebted to you for actual kindness and expressions of
               your good opinion. It is very delightful to enjoy the approbation of those who are
               themselves worthy of all praise and, whether worthy or unworthy myself, I certainly
               have that enjoyment on reading your letters. I am afraid that those around me will
               become jealous if you continue still to express yourself as you have done; at the
               same time it shall not be for want of exertion on my part in doing all that I can
               that you shall have cause to cease to do so. I have before complained to you of my
               want of understanding in the high branches of science with which you can delight
               &amp; instruct yourself and you will, I am sure, therefore forgive me for not being
               able at once to follow you in the beautiful train of reasoning &amp; demonstration
               which you have pursued and given rise to. I am really almost ashamed of the
               objections I made to the free admission of your theory for it accords so well with
               all the facts I can see that I ought perhaps to have allowed that what I could not
               see was invisible to me merely through the imperfection of my own perceptive powers.
               I have lately received many presents from you and one not many days ago from Mr.
               <persName>Underwood</persName>. I prise them very much and again offer my thanks for them. I wish I had
               other papers of equal consequence to return for them but from their scarcity you will
               be content perhaps to wait a long time for one. Mr. <persName>Underwood</persName> spoke in warm terms of
               your kind feelings towards me inasmuch that I could hardly have thought it possible
               to be as he said for I fell no merit on my part that can claim such good will. I may
               however well comprehend the cause in your own liberal feeling and I may easily admit
               that to be the source of your good opinion from the constant liberality of sentiment
               I have experienced in all the French Philosophers. Though comparatively young in
               science, I have still had occasion to experience something of the influence of those
               around me and I am compelled to say I have not found that kindness candour and
               liberality at home which I have now on several occasions uniformly experienced from
               the Parisian men of Science. I have written you rather a long letter considering
               there is no scientific news in it but I was anxious to acknowledge justly the favours
               I owe you and to say how highly I do esteem and shall esteem every mark of your
               kindness and friendship. Considering the very subordinate situation I hold here and
               the little encouragement which circumstances hold out to me, I have more than once
               been tempted to resign scientific pursuits altogether but then the remembrance of
               such letters &amp; expressions as yours cheers me again and I struggle on in hopes of
               getting results at one time or another that shall by their novelty or interest raise
               me into a more liberal and active sphere. I am Dear Sir your very obliged &amp;
               faithful Servant M. <persName>Faraday</persName>
          </foreign>
        </p>
            <closer> M. <persName>Ampère</persName>, &amp;c &amp;c </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>